A Guide to the Records of the Virginia Racing Commission, 1993-2008.
Library of Virginia
Library of Virginia
Racing Commission, Virginia, Records
1993-2008.
The Library of Virginia
43956, 51013
Virginia. Commission on Local Government.
24 cubic feet
Biographical/Historical Information
The Virginia Racing Commission was enacted in November 1988 and began meeting in 1989. The Commission consisted of five members appointed by the governor and confirmed by a majority of the General Assembly for a five-year term. The commissioners, in turn, appoint an executive secretary who serves as the agency head. The mission of the Virginia Racing Commission according to its strategic plan is "to promote, sustain, grow, and control a native horse racing industry with pari-mutuel wagering by prescribing regulations and conditions that command and promote excellence and complete honesty and integrity in racing and wagering." The Commission issues licenses for the construction, ownership, and operation of unlimited horse racing facilities and limited license race meetings. The Commission also issues permits to all persons participating in these races. On 12 October 1994, the Commission voted to issue an unlimited license to Stansley Management to construct, own, and operate a racetrack. This racetrack, Colonial Downs, opened on 1 September 1997 in New Kent County. Colonial Downs is now owned by Jeffrey and Richard Jacobs' Jacobs Entertainment.
Simulcasting of horseracing began in Virginia in 1991. In 1992, the General Assembly approved legislation permitting up to six satellite-wagering facilities in Virginia. Chesapeake opened the first satellite facility on 18 February 1996. A second satellite facility opened in Richmond on December 10. Hampton and Brunswick satellite facilities were opened in 1997. Still more satellite facilities opened in South Richmond in 2003 and Vinton in 2004. In 2004, the General Assembly amended the Racing Act to permit up to ten satellite-wagering facilities. Referendums passed in Westmoreland, Henry, and Scott counties to open facilities in Martinsville and a second facility in Chesapeake in 2005, and a facility in Scott County in 2006.
In 2003, a new statute was enacted requiring the Commission to license and regulate advance deposit account wagering companies operating in Virginia. As of 2007, The Virginia racing Commission oversaw one live horse racing facility at Colonial Downs, nine satellite-wagering facilities, and four advance deposit account wagering companies
Scope and Content
XX
Various arrangements. Records have been kept in their original order.
Acquisition Information
Accession 43956 was transferred by the Virginia Racing Commission, October 2, 2008.
Accession 40541 was transferred by the Virginia Racing Commission, August 21, 2013.
Contents List
- Records, 1993-2008 (Accession 43956)., Extent: 14 cubic feet (14 boxes)
  - Minutes and Transcripts, 1999-2006.
    - Minutes and Transcripts, 1999-2000. (Box 1)
    - Minutes and Transcripts, 2001-2003. (Box 2)
    - Minutes and Transcripts, 2004-2005. (Box 3)
    - Minutes and Transcripts, 2006. (Box 4)
  - Hearing files, 1993-1994.
    - Hearing Files, 1993-1994. (Box 5)
    - Hearing Files, 1993-1994. (Box 6)
    - Hearing Files, 1993-1994. (Box 7)
    - Hearing Files, 1993-1994. (Box 8)
  - Director's Correspondence and subject files (Stan Bowker), 1997-2008.
    - Correspondence and subject files, 1997-2008. (Box 9)
    - Correspondence and subject files, 1997-2008. (Box 10)
    - Correspondence and subject files, 1997-2008. (Box 11)
    - Correspondence and subject files, 1997-2008. (Box 12)
    - Correspondence and subject files, 1997-2008. (Box 13)
  - Annual Reports, 1997-2002.
    - Annual Reports, 1997-2002. (Box 14)
  - Architectural Drawings, 1993.
    - Architectural drawings (Old Dominion Jockey Club), 1993. (Box 14)
- Records, 1999-2008 (Accession 51013)., Extent: 10 cubic feet (10 boxes)
  - Director's correspondence and subject files (Stanley K. Bowker), 1999-2005.
    - Prince William Circuit Court Order on Referendum Certification, 1999. (Box 1)
    - Letter to Mr. Weinburg regarding Colonial Downs application, 1999. (Box 1)
    - Bowker letter to Stewart on incomplete / missing information on application, 1999. (Box 1)
    - Letter from Delegate Marshall, 1999. (Box 1)
    - Letter from Prince William County General Assembly Delegation, 1999. (Box 1)
    - Letter from Bowker to State Police requesting assistance on background investigations, 1999. (Box 1)
    - Bowker response to Delegation letter, 1999. (Box 1)
    - Letter from Leonard Hale on Colonial Downs steeplechase plans, 1999. (Box 1)
    - Sign-up sheets for Dumfries Public Meeting, 1999. (Box 1)
    - Transcript from Dumfries Public Meeting, 1999. (Box 1)
    - State Police, 1999. (Box 1)
    - Letter from Bowker to Stewart regarding "Net Entity", 1999. (Box 1)
    - Press Release on informal conference, 1999. (Box 1)
    - Notice to Appellants on informal conference, 1999. (Box 1)
    - Legal notice on informal conference, 1999. (Box 1)
    - Colonial Downs response to request for additional information, 1999. (Box 1)
    - Colonial Downs amendment, 1999. (Box 1)
    - Colonial Downs rebuttal submission, 1999. (Box 1)
    - Colonial Downs exhibits at informal fact finding conference, 1999. (Box 1)
    - Colonial Downs / VaHBPA term sheet, 1999. (Box 1)
    - Crowe Chisek report, 1999. (Box 1)
    - County of New Kent filing, 1999. (Box 1)
    - VaHBPA Resolution, 1999. (Box 1)
    - Letter from Gillan Gordon-Moore, 1999. (Box 1)
    - Virginia Horsemens Association memo, 1999. (Box 1)
    - Colonial Downs - additional information, 1999. (Box 1)
    - Media Advisory for 11/1/1999 IFF, 1999. (Box 1)
    - Environmental Site Assessment Potomac CDD Landfill, 1999. (Box 1)
    - Dumfries Economic Impact, 1999. (Box 1)
    - Colonial Downs response to New Kent County opposing Northern Virginia racetrack, 1999. (Box 1)
    - Sheriff Dept. - New Kent, 1999. (Box 1)
    - Virginia Turf Club, 1999. (Box 1)
    - New Kent - Colonial Downs, L.P. Stansley Racing and Virginia Turf Club, 1999. (Box 1)
    - Colonial Downs proposed findings of fact, 1999. (Box 1)
    - Virginia Turf Association - pending license in Prince William County, 1999. (Box 1)
    - Transcript of Colonial Downs IFFC, 1999. (Box 1)
    - Research, 1999-2005. (Box 2)
    - New Richmond, 1999-2005. (Box 2)
    - Records Management, 1999-2005. (Box 2)
    - Request for pools, 1999-2005. (Box 2)
    - Inspections, 1999-2005. (Box 2)
    - Homeland Security, 1999-2005. (Box 2)
    - VITA, 1999-2005. (Box 2)
    - Account Wagering - Secondary, 1999-2005. (Box 2)
    - Account Wagering - Primary, 1999-2005. (Box 2)
    - Horsemen's bookkeeping, 1999-2005. (Box 2)
    - EDR, 1999-2005. (Box 2)
    - White Collar Exemption Changes, 1999-2005. (Box 2)
    - Supertest, 1999-2005. (Box 2)
    - Trainer Andrew Dion, 1999-2005. (Box 2)
    - Jockey insurance, 1999-2005. (Box 2)
    - Ruel appeal, 1999-2005. (Box 2)
    - Miscellaneous, 1999-2005. (Box 2)
    - Employee fraud, 1999-2005. (Box 2)
    - Necropsy findings, 1999-2005. (Box 2)
    - Colonial Downs 2005 Improvements, 1999-2005. (Box 2)
    - MEC Officers and Directors, 1999-2005. (Box 2)
    - DSAS, 1999-2005. (Box 2)
    - USTA, 1999-2005. (Box 2)
    - Surplus Property Guidelines, 1999-2005. (Box 2)
    - Governor's Commission on Efficiency and Effectiveness, 1999-2005. (Box 2)
    - Kibler, 1999-2005. (Box 2)
    - Records Management - ongoing, 1999-2005. (Box 2)
    - Surveys, 1999-2005. (Box 2)
    - Legal, 1999-2005. (Box 2)
    - Performance measures, 1999-2005. (Box 2)
    - Workforce Plan, 1999-2005. (Box 2)
    - Governor, 1999-2005. (Box 2)
    - Aviation, Dept. of, 1999-2005. (Box 2)
    - LePage, Shirley, 1999-2005. (Box 2)
    - Performance measures, 2004-2006. (Box 6)
    - Strategic Plan, 2004-2006. (Box 6)
    - SWAM, 2004-2006. (Box 6)
    - Handbook for Agency Heads, 2004-2006. (Box 6)
    - Attorney General, 2004-2006. (Box 6)
    - Youbet Issues, 2004-2006. (Box 6)
  - Original transcripts and minutes, 2007-2008.
    - Original transcripts and minutes, 2007 Jan. (Box 3)
    - Original transcripts and minutes, 2007 Feb. (Box 3)
    - Original transcripts and minutes, 2007 Mar. (Box 3)
    - Original transcripts and minutes, 2007 Apr. (Box 3)
    - Original transcripts and minutes, 2007 May. (Box 3)
    - Original transcripts and minutes, 2007 June. (Box 3)
    - Original transcripts and minutes, 2007 July. (Box 3)
    - Original transcripts and minutes, 2007 Aug. (Box 3)
    - Original transcripts and minutes, 2007 Sept. (Box 3)
    - Original transcripts and minutes, 2007 Oct. (Box 3)
    - Original transcripts and minutes, 2007 Nov. (Box 3)
    - Original transcripts and minutes, 2007 Dec. (Box 3)
    - Original transcripts and minutes, 2008 Jan. (Box 3)
    - Original transcripts and minutes, 2008 Feb. (Box 3)
    - Original transcripts and minutes, 2008 Mar. (Box 3)
    - Original transcripts and minutes, 2008 Apr. (Box 3)
    - Original transcripts and minutes, 2008 May. (Box 3)
    - Original transcripts and minutes, 2008 June. (Box 3)
    - Original transcripts and minutes, 2008July. (Box 3)
    - Original transcripts and minutes, 2008 Aug. (Box 3)
    - Original transcripts and minutes, 2008 Sept. (Box 3)
    - Original transcripts and minutes, 2008 Oct. (Box 3)
    - Original transcripts and minutes, 2008 Nov. (Box 3)
    - Original transcripts and minutes, 2008 Dec. (Box 3)
  - Director's correspondence and subject files (Victor I. Harrison), 2008.
    - Tracks, 2008. (Box 4)
    - Agriculture, Dept. of, 2008. (Box 4)
    - eVa, 2008. (Box 4)
    - EZ Horseplay, 2008. (Box 4)
    - Findings, 2008. (Box 4)
    - General Fund, 2008. (Box 4)
    - Grant requests, 2008. (Box 4)
    - Handle Analysis, 2008. (Box 4)
    - HTA - TRA, 2008. (Box 4)
    - Hunt Club, 2008. (Box 4)
    - Ian's spreadsheets, 2008. (Box 4)
    - Instant Racing, 2008. (Box 4)
    - IHRA 1978, 2008. (Box 4)
    - IT, 2008. (Box 4)
    - Jockey Health Information System, 2008. (Box 4)
    - LAB, 2008. (Box 4)
    - Miscellaneous, 2008. (Box 4)
    - Lease, 2008. (Box 4)
    - Legislation, 2008. (Box 4)
    - Letters, 2008. (Box 4)
    - Licenses (Approvals), 2008. (Box 4)
    - Marketing, 2008. (Box 4)
    - Mediators, 2008. (Box 4)
    - Medications, 2008. (Box 4)
    - Minutes, 2008. (Box 4)
    - Model rules, 2008. (Box 4)
    - NRC, 2008. (Box 4)
    - New bet types, 2008. (Box 4)
    - PA Gaming Congress, 2008. (Box 4)
    - PA Rules, 2008. (Box 4)
    - Payroll, 2008. (Box 4)
    - Performance measures, 2008. (Box 4)
    - Permits, 2008. (Box 4)
    - Policies / Procedures, 2008. (Box 4)
    - Phones, 2008. (Box 4)
    - Positives, 2008. (Box 4)
    - Preparedness, 2008. (Box 4)
    - Productivity, 2008. (Box 4)
    - Project Hoofbeat, 2008. (Box 4)
    - Public Participation Guidelines, 2008. (Box 4)
    - Racing Days, 2008. (Box 4)
    - Racing Officials, 2008. (Box 4)
    - Racing Summit, 2008. (Box 4)
    - RMTC, 2008. (Box 4)
    - Reception, 2008. (Box 4)
    - Resources, 2008. (Box 4)
    - ROAP, 2008. (Box 4)
    - Security, 2008. (Box 4)
    - Sports Wagering, 2008. (Box 4)
    - Staff meeting, 2008. (Box 4)
    - Steeplechases, 2008. (Box 4)
    - Steroids, 2008. (Box 4)
    - Stewards / Judges, 2008. (Box 4)
    - SWAM, 2008. (Box 4)
    - SWFs, 2008. (Box 4)
    - Telecommuting, 2008. (Box 4)
    - Telephone account wagering, 2008. (Box 4)
    - Test Barn, 2008. (Box 4)
    - THG, 2008. (Box 4)
    - TVG, 2008. (Box 4)
    - TRA 20/20, 2008. (Box 4)
    - Travel regulations, 2008. (Box 4)
    - Triple Crown nominees, 2008. (Box 4)
    - Tucson, 2008. (Box 4)
    - Twin Spires, 2008. (Box 4)
    - Unpaid fines, 2008. (Box 4)
    - USTA, 2008. (Box 4)
    - Veterinarian, 2008. (Box 4)
    - Virginia, 2008. (Box 4)
    - VITA, 2008. (Box 4)
    - VTA, 2008. (Box 4)
    - Wagering types, 2008. (Box 4)
    - Workplates, 2008. (Box 4)
    - HR, 2008. (Box 4)
    - Transcript copy 2008. (Box 5)
    - Harness detail, 2008. (Box 5)
    - Virginia Racing Commission - Minutes, 2002. (Box 5)
    - Virginia Racing Commission - Minutes, 2003. (Box 5)
    - Virginia Racing Commission - Minutes, 2004. (Box 5)
    - Virginia Racing Commission - Minutes, 2005. (Box 5)
    - Virginia Racing Commission - Minutes, 2006. (Box 5)
    - Audit, 2008. (Box 5)
    - Bonus, 2008. (Box 5)
    - AAEP, 2008. (Box 5)
    - ADW, 2008. (Box 5)
    - Agency scorecard, 2008. (Box 5)
    - Agency Heads, 2008. (Box 5)
    - AITRs, 2008. (Box 5)
    - Amtote, 2008. (Box 5)
    - Animal Clubs, 2008. (Box 5)
    - Animal Cruelty, 2008. (Box 5)
    - Annual Report, 2008. (Box 5)
    - ARCF, 2008. (Box 5)
    - Arizona, 2008. (Box 5)
    - Audit, 2008. (Box 5)
    - Bowker - Miscellaneous, 2008. (Box 5)
    - Breeder's Fund, 2008. (Box 5)
    - Calendar months, 2008. (Box 5)
    - Catastrophic injuries, 2008. (Box 5)
    - Colonial Downs race dates, 2008. (Box 5)
    - Certified return receipts, 2008. (Box 5)
    - Colonial Downs sale, 2008. (Box 5)
    - C and T, 2008. (Box 5)
    - Commissioners, 2008. (Box 5)
    - Committees, 2008. (Box 5)
    - Complaints, 2008. (Box 5)
    - Contacts, 2008. (Box 5)
    - COVA, 2008. (Box 5)
    - Dan's Handicapping, 2008. (Box 5)